hello welcome to episode 5 of the bmv
connection today's episode is going to
be on good versus bad exercises and also
best exercise uh with me as Brad
Schoenfeld Brad do you want to introduce
this topic sure we've discussed over the
years how we kind of don't like the
terms good or bad exercise certainly my
one of my mentors and else if I had
coined the phrase there are there's no
such thing as good or as general rule
there's no such thing as good or bad
exercise when we pour application of
poor performance of the exercise and I
think both of us to a large extent
concur with that philosophy um so sore
with one caveat uh you depends on the
person of course you know there are bad
exercises for some people but um so what
would you say to someone who just
recently wrote a blog post saying if you
could only do one exercise if you could
only do one lift I think we have to
banish that person to the iron made I
thought it was funny because I thought
of you and I wrote that cuz those annoy
the hell out of you know what is
actually different I mean you would you
propose was really different if that
wasn't a good or bad exercise that's
giving some of limitations as to what
they can do forcing them into an
exercise I see a difference there well
anyway I always loved bees I love these
types of questions because they get me
to think but why the hell would anyone
has anyone in the world ever been a
situation where they can only do one
exercise anyway uh yeah this topic is
different this this topic you see it a
lot in magazines don't do this do this
or five exercise you should never do and
things like this and I want to mention
that you and you and I both are both
inspired by bodybuilding wears a lot of
strength coaches and physical therapists
have no
for you they've never delved into the
bodybuilding world much and they they
take up more like a they look at things
in a more kind of like a functional
anatomy type you know so I actually
wrote an article on T nation god this
was several years ago I remember because
I was in Auckland and I came up with the
idea like ten o'clock at night and I
decided to work on it until like ten
o'clock the next morning I just didn't
sleep that night that's back when I was
in my manic mode but it was called the
new rules of lifting and it was one of
my favorite articles but a lot of people
only got like half way through the
article and we're flipping out on me
because I started off explaining why you
shouldn't do every exercise you remember
that one and and my point my whole point
was you could make any excuse to not
like an exercise you could you know I
give me any exercise the squad I could
make it if if you if I wanted to I could
make a compelling case while you
shouldn't squat why you shouldn't dead
live why you shouldn't bench press I
could also make a very compelling case
while you should just depending on how I
worded things so I guess let's talk
about what what are the most demonized
exercises let's talk about that first
yeah i do before getting into that one
to just point out when you mention that
a lot of people come from a strength and
conditioning perspective or a functional
perspective I think that really that's
one of the problems here is that really
we should not dictate what someone
should do it's really a good fitness
professional is going to adhere to
whatever the goals of that person are so
yeah if you're just working if you're in
strength conditioning coach for a
basketball team then you're working with
a given population you could say for
that population I don't think these
exercises should be done for whatever
reason but to just cast them aspersion
on on the exercise in general really
misses out on the point that really
training is specific to the individual
so sorry for not not I usually agree
with it so okay so what what exerciser
most commonly demonized behind the neck
moves and I would actually probably give
that I would never see a reason to do it
behind the neck lat pulldown just
because you really get the same benefit
from pull down to the front and there's
less air at rest but for the most part
the lab buddy behind the neck presses or
pull downs upright rows I wrote a whole
article on that to the strength
conditioning journal leg extensions
crunches we wrote a very controversial
parently controversial article on spinal
flexion there's just so many dips is
when a hero I act deck okay well let's
talk about some of these exercises the
one that cracks me up the most is leg
extensions um because uh the reason why
people will what's the word I'm looking
for like will bash leg extensions the
reason why is they'll say they'll talk
about this stress the stress is to the
ACL right is that what you commonly hear
ya in which case the ACL they'll they'll
mention like what like the tensile
forces that are put on the ACL and the
ACL but what they don't mention is that
the ACL is it represents only a fraction
of what the ACL can withstand it's like
not even I mean do not do leg extensions
because it's because of the ACL is not a
good reason why didn't why you shouldn't
do them I agree totally first of all
it's based on the premise that in a
single joint open-chain movement the
hamstrings will not go contract
hamstrings actually provide a counter
balance to the anterior tibial
translation so that without the
hamstrings co contracting with the quads
the ACL is going to bear the brunt of
the of the interior shear force but
again as you point out you're not
getting significantly actual shape if
you actually measure the shear forces
there well handled by the ACL but by
healthy a CMS really is a partition so
some people some people who like you you
any exercise and there's going to be a
certain percentage of people who don't
who don't like them it doesn't feel
right and this goes for every exercise
and I think a lot of times authors for
example someone who has bad shoulders or
a bad back or a bad knees and they feel
a certain exercise is dangerous for them
they just assume that all this has got
to apply to everyone so nobody should do
this and that's one challenge we have as
fitness writers and why you should talk
to other people and watch the way they
trained and have a lot of lifting
partners and friends and things like
that in the gym because when you talk to
people you realize not you know the
human bodies are very unique and you
can't just and people have different
goals and I will tell you I can't you
know I have a lot of bodybuilding
friends who have been doing exercises
for years and these exercise that are
you know contraindicated but they've
learned how to make it work for them so
there are subtle ways to do exercises in
which case uh let's talk about the
individual exercise so we were talking
about leg extensions right why would you
not want to do like it where would you
let splits maybe it would be a good idea
to talk about where we're like
extensions would be valuable and where
they might not be valuable so for
example leg extensions are very valuable
neri neri habilitation and bodybuilding
our leg extensions as important for wood
leg extensions be a good exercise for
the strength coach who has two hours a
week with the athletes no it would not
because you could be doing quote unquote
more functional exercises that maybe I
could you know squatting or single leg
type knee dominant movements however
maybe the guy who has terribly weak
quads maybe it would be worthwhile for
him to do it so yeah so if someone at is
very just generally doesn't happen but
if they're very hip dominant where
they're they're glutes are just really
overpowering the quads and
can see the way you can you can find the
reason there but that's what you are
level I mean what you often hear is well
why would you ever do a leg extension
because it's the most non functional
exercise and again it's missing we wrote
the article on our single joint
exercises functions commented missing
the boat number one you don't look good
things in a vacuum you don't forget no
one just those leg extensions but you
won't even point that out there was a
study pipe fitter own back in nineteen
ninety the classic study done in the
nursing home nursing home patients on 90
year old the nursing home patients who
just did leg extensions three sets of
leg extensions three times a week for
eight weeks and two of the ten subjects
were able to throw away their canes and
walk without canceled if you're saying
that's not walking isn't functional I
have a problem so again functional
that's the we could do a whole separate
podcast on functional but but going back
to ok so leg extensions why are they a
good idea for bodybuilders if you're
already doing squats what can leg
extensions possibly add that squads
aren't taken care of well you're
focusing getting more focused tension on
the quads and allows you number one it
can increase the metabolic stress
because of the because of the single
joint you of movement you can we've
actually discussed this before but you
can generate greater localize the
localized punk within those muscles than
you can with a the squat with a multi
joint and greater oxia yep greater and
so let's chose just show you the you if
you told a bodybuilder throw out leg
extensions they laugh at you because
it's a valuable tool it's not their only
leg exercise they do a variety of
quadricep exercises but they they all
love the leg extension they do it for
high reps for the most point you know
most most bodybuilders will do like four
sets of 20 with a lighter loads trying
to really focus on that constant tension
to achieve maximal pump and you know
burn and occlusion
so uh and we talked about last podcast a
recent study that came out was at Mia
miyamura what was it emo Miyamoto
Miyamoto where the leg extension
actually had greater hypertrophy or
greater occlusion they have the same
activation throughout the whole
quadricep but it actually got more
occlusion in the distal region which
jives with what body builders will tell
you that the lake leg extension is you
know good at building the lower quads so
they're good there's a reason why you
should do like extensions if your goals
are quadriceps hypertrophy their
invaluable tool all right what about
other exercise we talked about behind
the neck presses and upright rows and
behind the neck pull downs one thing
that I've always noticed as a strength
coach a lot of people you will see they
lose shoulder mobility and it's funny a
lot of things a lot of things we do like
scapular wall slides look like a behind
the neck press or pull down and so I
remember when I used to do behind the
neck presses all the time and I read
that they're not good for you I stop
doing them and then one day I went and
tried doing behind the neck presses
again and it felt really tight just
didn't feel right well back when I was
doing on if they felt right but I
obviously lost some of my nobility so I
would surmise that there would be a
sweet spot between doing an exercise and
maintaining mobility without overdoing
it to where you're causing damages now
Brad tell me if I am in this position
here why is this risky well the
combination of a deduction shoulder a
deduction and external rotation puts the
shoulder into a position where it you
call it the high five position that's
the high five position correct uh and
studies have shown
friend and colleague of mine Laura
Cobras looked at this shown that that
places the shoulder in a position where
it can be damaged more readily and that
goes with PEC deck do we do the
traditional at deck in the high five
position that's all silver and then how
did the talk about how an upright row is
different from that well the upright row
because you are and now this I actually
wrote a paper on actually with morrie
was a collaborator on that but a a
position of a deduction and internal
rotation beyond 90 degrees puts the
rotator cuff in a position where it can
be engaged for purse pineda standin can
be impinged at the butt again now this
goes back to or wanted your guy that
comes what did you guys recommend for
that if that's a concern yeah what's
been shown is that as long as you do not
go past so this really is the move if
you stay within this range you do not
risk impingement that really impeachment
is what people do is they do this they
pull up so that the elbows are higher
than the risk that will come all the way
up and they'll go beyond the 90 degrees
to a point so anywhere between this like
80 to 90 degree degree as long as you're
not going past roughly parallel with the
ground you're fine I recommend using a
wider grip is you're doing it which
really forces you you use the closer
grip it kind of allows you wasn't there
also a study that showed that wider grip
activated more deltoid anyway we're
middle delts yeah that's again why it
bases you into greater a production and
really the benefits you want to talk
about benefit why would you ever do that
just a little lateral raise well you can
use it because it's a multi joint move
it allows you to increase the amount of
weight that you're using above the
lateral raise those you're getting
greater mechanical tension ah now on the
muscle and da Brat a heaven computer yes
it's working now okay that all right all
right now something you just said
there's struck a chord with me you're
using greater load so you're going
have greater mechanical tension I do not
agree with that like on the deltoids it
would be you would look at the load
versus the lever lengths the distance
out from the shoulder joint so with the
lateral raise you could have a very
light load but since it's so far out you
have if you're creating calculating
torque you would look at both the moment
arm the moment of the resistance arm and
the load whereas with an upright row
it's not going to be as far out if you
wanted to know which place more tension
on the deltoid you would the best way
for us to estimate would be to look at a
muscle activation however variety we
talked about variety last week you're
going to activate different just let me
just challenge you on that island would
also i have not measured torque on on
the two exercises but multi-joint moves
just traditionally you're going to it
increases your ability to to increase
the overall torque will be greater you
could say that other muscles are taking
up some of the the forces they are words
with anna lateral raise a role on the
anterior delt you'd have to measure that
out but a chest press is always going to
give you greater you can move more
weight and those more weight right but
you as far as tension on the muscles you
think so you're thinking they're like
like a if you look at chummily chest
press yeah like you've seen the studies
on for example bench press dumbbell
bench and flies I think they all had
similar activation trying to think of my
uh my EMG studies I was well this
activation is different don't remember
again that beyond when you activation
looks at recruitment so let's sure you
can have full recruitment that's so if
you're just looking purely at the EMG
that's not really fair because the
recruitment doesn't tell you the amount
of but that's our best way to estimate
right now no those your recruiting all
the muscle fibers you still might have a
greater load under the fibers at that
point we
whether that actually translates into
greater greater hypertrophic response
that remains to be determined we haven't
any studies that are looking at that but
greater forces even you can have two
different exercises that produce the
same amount of activation but you're
still having greater forces acting in
one just because once you max out
activation you're anything greater
forces do you mean greater muscle horses
well correct greater that there's the
muscles are under greater a greater load
there barring a greater amount of force
through the so they're maxed out you can
max out recruitment so that you caused
all the fibers to recruit but there's
still a greater load that's being lifted
/ fiber area so i have a whole folder
with EMG and muscle force with isometric
exercises it's very like one-to-one
there's a almost a perfect correlations
with dynamic exercises it's different
and under fatigue it's not accurate but
generally speaking EMG activation and
muscle force is pretty it's a pretty
it's a good it's a good monitor of
muscle force it's our best way our best
easy way to measure tension on the
muscle if you needed to actually
calculate muscle forces now we're going
into very very advanced biomechanical
measurements here where you use the most
popular ways to use inverse dynamics and
muscle modeling in which case now you've
got to stand on a force plate you need 9
it'll you know like motion you know like
cameras around the room picking up
motion capture with EMG with everything
else and then you're feeding forward
information about the muscles themselves
and where they attach and things like
that and the properties of the muscles
and you're using inverse dynamics to try
to determine the muscle forces and
there's a lot of assumptions in there
that have to be made and it's it's a
fascinating science but but that's
actually another topic we can talk about
how you know with muscle forces itself
I actually don't agree with it i don't
think that heavier way our compound
exercises uh what I say you could get
the same results doing all isolation
movements versus compound that's a tough
one because I would say you know we
always a strength training writers say
do do compound movements because you can
get way better results if you focus on
the bench press the military press the
squat the deadlift the you know heavy
row or chin up you're going to see a lot
better results than doing all these
isolation movements but at the end of
the day I think hypertrophy all comes
down to what you're telling the muscles
to do which I learn from your article
the three ways and I think of the
individual muscles themselves and how
much activation is going on in the
different muscles and the stim that you
know like the signaling stimuli the
mechanotransduction and then the
different pathways and so if you did
enough isolation movements to talk to
target to stimulate all those muscles
that I think you could and and it's
funny I've seen some bodybuilders come
back from you know for looking at
certain guys routines that I'm like
dangly and it granted they're on a
million different steroids but they do a
ton of isolation stuff and in it and it
works for them but that's now we're
getting off topic here we're talking
about exercises and contraindicated
exercises we were talking about behind
the neck presses and upright rows and
things like that all right let's give us
an area where you would not want to use
on versus where you would want to use
them so i can think of training a I'm an
athlete who wants to stay healthy I
would never give them upright rows or
behind the net presence I don't know if
I'd agree with that I'm you know to get
an upright rows very safe exercise of
don't crowd well I wouldn't get the
standard way to come up most people
anyway right
I would have them stop with the arms
parallel to 90 degrees um however I got
flooded when you're training an athlete
well I mean there's it's so much
specificity that you're really looking
at and things like muscle-bound
imbalances and balances and so many of
the factors that you really need to
consider in that so that really gets
very murky everything else kind of Arc
even when you're talking obviously this
even with your general client you have
to look at injuries and other things but
athletes just a perso specific to a
given sport and not only sport but a
position generally often it's in team
sports to give a position that they're
playing so it kind of gets a little hard
to make recommendations well but I would
I guess my point is where I would employ
these exercises would be with
bodybuilders looking to maximize
hypertrophy in this situation and then
Olympic lifters will sometimes do like
behind the neck push presses are jerks
or things like that though they'll do
various movements that kind of resemble
upright rowing like high poles and stuff
in which case they would most Olympic
weightlifters would say that the arms
are just passive you're exploding at the
hips but then I talk to other Olympic
good Olympic weightlifters they say no
you are pulling with the arms a little
bit so that's a tent that's its own
separate discussion but it depends on
what I'm trying to say is it all depends
on the situation oh I would never
there's never a scenario that I don't
know where I would use it on the neck
lat pulldown because there's been
studies that have looked at lat
pulldowns to the back versus the front
the front pulled out actually has
greater activation of the intestines
Dorsai I don't have not seen any studies
now maybe you can argue that you get
slightly different activation in the
very variety within it was slightly
think of behind the neck worked more mid
trap and rhomboid I don't remember
seeing that but but bottom line
is that me you start to get into a bad
cost-benefit there because of how you
have to come back to really first of all
those issues with the neck push pushing
down I just don't like the movement what
I have a problem of some of the thought
they can integrate it no se but it's not
really for me everything is cost benefit
I just don't think really there's much
at that point the cost really or higher
than the benefits I think that we can
argue it's not not that it's a bad
exercise I just think it's less good
well so what you said is most people do
that to target the lats and you're
actually getting less latissimus dorsi
activation compared with front pull
downs but you are getting more
activation and other fibers but most
people do them there might be there are
probably other exercises that are better
at recruiting the mid traps and the
rhomboids so okay and couple more topics
to discuss we still haven't broached
upon best exercise but before we talk
about that we've only got about five
minutes left we didn't discuss spinal
movement crunches so usually you see
articles that are you know nobody should
ever crunch ever again I would say this
movement was championed by Stu McGill
and then a lot of strength coaches
jumped on board and at that time people
were doing you know like we weren't
monitoring this you had bodybuilders
doing god I've seen cases where they do
it like thousands by the thousands of
crunches some of them in which case I
think that is very foolish but in our
paper we talked about range of motion
posture volume things like that I myself
see no problem if I for example layover
a Swiss ball I'm in some you know I
marched over it into some extension I
put like a 25 pound dumbbell here and I
move mostly at the thoracic spine and my
lumbar spine stays
it doesn't move into much flexion at all
but I use a controlled tempo and I lower
it slowly I get to 15 reps and I'm
burning my abs are burning so bad people
would say people they argued be made
well why not just do an ab will roll out
are you going to achieve any more
additional musculature in the abdominal
region if you do the dynamic exercise I
would argue yes you would but you've got
to be pretty lean to see the hood the if
you're not lean you're not going to see
that extra hypertrophy anyway so again
it depends on the population if you're
looking at bodybuilders who want that
extra abdominal muscle then you should
probably do it if you're just if you're
not looking to maximize your hypertrophy
maybe just do core stability exercise
the point is it all depends on the
situation by the by the way Brett I
think it's also important to point out
that it's not like we're huge champions
of the crunch and I think sometimes
people think that because we wrote this
article that means that hey we just
surround a crunch whole day and really
jus it came down to what we're talking
about now is that the demonization of an
exercise that's been a staple exercise
program was it warranted and based on
the literature just is it but the fact
that the to say that no one should be
doing crunches or that you should be
saving your spinal flexion to tie your
shoes simply is not consistent with the
literature we I think very clearly
showed that in our article which is
really no one has challenged in if
anything that we've said even even dr.
McGill is coming out and said there is
no such thing as good or bad exercises
only differ different populations so
well done I'm gonna play devil's
advocate isn't consistent with the
literature there's no literature showing
that it does that it's not dangerous
that the bulk of the literature shows
that it is dangerous but we pointed out
reasons why you would want to be
doubtful of the literature because we
have not seen that in humans in vivo
we've just seen it with pig spines in
vitro and which I don't think the pitch
this is not
but you said the literature does show
that the literature literature shows
that an ex-vivo pig spine when subjected
to many thousands of spinal flexion
cycles in a continuous fashion Walton
Ernie that is very different from saying
that the cool in there is really no
evidence point out the a lack of
evidence does not mean that so an
absence of evidence is not evidence of
absence so could it happen yet as we
talked about but clearly not only did we
point out that the literature doesn't
show this there's anything has been very
overly extrapolated what what people
looking at but there is evidence that
there is benefits too we talked about
cause benefit that we talked about
pumping fluid into the into the discs
because they're poorly that's the
produce poor circulation to them so we
discussed how the rap actually can be
positive but factors not only for the
musculature but as the discs as well
from the remodeling standpoint that this
actually can remodel and that
potentially might have been
strengthening the disc so but in the
meantime in the meantime my position is
until more recently chuck i categorize
this up onto my shelf as more research
is needed I don't know what to think
exactly I know what's to McGill thinks I
know what you and I think I value his
opinion very much I think that if you
did a study in humans and Karen stuck to
our recommendations and did pre and post
MRIs you wouldn't see any evidence of
additional damage over a control group
but that research is not out there so in
the meantime you can make your decision
and say I'm either going to play it safe
and not do these this exercise or if I
do do it I'm going to listen to what
Brad and brett said I'm going to do them
mostly in my throat so my lumbar spine
isn't moving to full range of motion I'm
going to limit live vol I'm gonna you
know i'm not going to do three sets of a
thousand crunches when you do them in a
controlled fashion in
squeeze and you know it's a lot harder
you can you know you can do them in a
way where 20 is hard now I've taking
clients and taught them that so the
level of stress you're putting on the
spine is going to be way less doing 20
compared to a thousand and you you can
do them with very limited range of
motion one study showed that if you
limit the bending from 13 degrees down
to 11 in one motion segment you get
fifty percent of the distress and we're
saying don't we're saying you only use a
very small fraction of your so we would
have way less stress I mean that's just
common physics so uh I agree with
everything you just said yep so a couple
minutes left let's talk about best
exercise selection um well actually
we're out of time this will be the first
one we're going over but I ramble I'm a
Rambler okay uh best exercises what's
the problem with that Brad
huh
best exercise visual a one best exercise
for everyone because it will depend upon
not only the person the person's needs
and goals and abilities but also what
they're what they're looking to do not
cut out there Brad he was choppy there
for a little bit um so repeat that yeah
I just said that it really will depend
on the individual what their needs their
goals and abilities are to give one
blanket statement like that squats are
the best exercise or dead lifts for the
best exerciser say these are things that
you can't determine about the person I
training trying to get one best
exercises in my opinion so it now I
happen to like these types of arguments
for example squats maybe I think squats
are the best leg exercise or dead lifts
are the best posterior chain exercise or
something like that but again it would
depend on the individual squats
shouldn't be performed by everyone
neither should deadlifts by everyone I
would it be okay to say look we we took
I want to know what's the best tech
exercise what's the best glute exercise
I took a hundred people and subjected to
them in a muscle activation and this one
averaged out to be the highest so I can
conclude that this is the best exercise
for this muscle but it's not only about
activation I mean it's about the person
so number one you have to take into
account potential injuries that have
been that have happened to the person um
get why they're functional roundel
occations if that's a goal so I mean if
you're talking about bodybuilding then
no one exercise is ever going to be
optimal to do everything that you need
to work a muscle from different angles
and we discuss this in our in our last
podcast so gimmick to me it just kind of
misses the boat it's simplistically
looking at a very complex topic so if
you're looking for athletes they'd want
to do you know they're going to want to
look more at the transfer
training if you're looking at
bodybuilders they're going to want to do
the exercise that build a muscle the
best in which case you're always going
to use a variety anyway because three
exercises well-planned exercises will be
better than one powerlifters it all
depends on their strength curves where
there are strong where they're weak
parts are so the best exercise is all
dependent on the individual and in
conclusion there are no good or bad
exercises just good form versus bad form
and good for the what good for the
person and bad for the person are not so
good for the person said Thank You
Bradley we will see you guys next week 4
episode 6